H. Freeman Matthews, Jr. Papers, 1947-1999 Finding Aid
Princeton University Library -- Manuscripts Collections
H. Freeman Matthews, Jr. Papers,
1947-1999
MC277
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections. Seeley G. Mudd Manuscript Library. Public Policy Papers. 65 Olden Street Princeton, New Jersey 08540 USA
2.0 linear ft. 2 boxes
Matthews, H. Freeman, Jr., 1927-2006
H. Freeman Matthews, Jr., son of H. Freeman Matthews, was a career Foreign Service officer, serving with the State Department from 1952 to 1991. The collection consists of materials documenting Matthews, Jr.'s service with the State Department, in particular, his time as Deputy Chief of Mission in Cairo from 1976 to 1980.
H. Freeman Matthews, Jr., Princeton University class of 1949, was a career Foreign Service officer, serving the State Department in a range of capacities from 1952 to 1985. Prior to his career with the State Department, Matthews, Jr. worked for the Central Hanover Bank & Trust Co. in New York. He joined the State Department in 1952 and served in Italy, Switzerland, Spain, Vietnam, and Mexico.
After returning from Mexico in 1974, he worked on the Garrison Diversion Unit project and became Director of Egyptian Affairs shortly thereafter. In 1976, the State Department transferred him to Egypt where he was Deputy Chief of Mission in Cairo from 1976 to 1980. He played a role in the peace negotians between Israel and Egypt, involving President Jimmy Carter, President Anwar Sadat, and Prime Minister Menachem Begin.
After returning from Egypt, Matthews, Jr. became a consultant with the Bureau of Diplomatic Security before officially retiring in 1985. After his retirement, he worked on the White House Iran-Contra Legal Task Force and Inter-Agency Review Committee from 1987 to 1991.
Matthews, Jr. died on July 22, 2006.
The H. Freeman Matthews, Jr. papers document his career in the State Department and contain subject files, newspaper clippings, photographs, and day planners. The majority of the papers are related to his time in Egypt in the late 1970s and his work on the Garrison Diversion Unit project.
The collection is open for research use.
Gift of Nancy Matthews in 2015.
The archivist separated two government publications from the collection.
Matthews, Nancy; Diplomatic and consular service, American -- Egypt -- 20th century.; Foreign Service; State Department Administration; Middle East -- Politics and government -- 20th century.; South Dakota -- Politics and government -- 20th century.; United States--Foreign relations--Middle East.; Born digital.; Public policy/20th century; Diplomacy
- Series I Cairo Files, 1976-1980; 1 boxes
  The archivist has not imposed any arrangement on these files.
  Series I: Cairo Files contains files documenting Matthews, Jr.'s time as Deputy Chief of Mission in Cairo from 1976 to 1980. The files contain background materials, momentos, news clippings, cultural information, and photographs.
  - Cairo Momentos, 1976-1980; portion of 1 box (Box 1)
  - Background Material, 1976-1980; portion of 1 box (Box 1)
  - Farewells - Cairo, 1980; portion of 1 box (Box 1)
  - Cairo - Cultural, 1977-1980; portion of 1 box (Box 1)
  - Newsclippings, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 1)
  - Photographs, undated; 1 box (Box 1, Box 2)
- Series II: Garrison Diversion Unit, 1973-1974; portion of 1 box
  Series II: Garrison Diversion Unit documents Matthews, Jr.'s time working on the international implications of the effort to divert water from the Garrison Dam for irrigation in North Dakota.
  - Correspondence, Notes, and Maps, 1974; portion of 1 box (Box 1)
  - Background Material, 1973; portion of 1 box (Box 1)
- Series III: General State Department Files, 1959-1999; portions of 2 boxes
  Series III: General State Department Files documents Matthews, Jr.'s day-to-day work and the award received.
  - Awards, 1969-1997; portion of 1 box (Box 1)
  - Mid Careers Course, 1959; portion of 1 box (Box 1)
  - Senior Seminar in Foreign Policy, 1973-1974; 1.0 folder (Box 1)
  - Service Plaque, 1985; portion of 1 box (Box 1)
  - Identification Documents, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 1)
  - Day Planners, 1970-1990; 1 box (Box 2)
- Series IV: Personal Materials, 1947; portion of 1 box
  Series IV: Personal Materials includes a letter written by H. Freeman Matthews, Jr. to his parents while in the army in 1947 as well as candid photographs and photographs of friends and colleagues.
  - Letter from H. Freeman Matthews, Jr. to his parents, 1947; portion of 1 box (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 1)